Okay, let's continue with our second part of today's lecture.
好的，让我们继续今天的讲座第二部分。好的，那我们就接着讲今天的课程第二部分吧。
Now we go to our lecture for about digital signature.
现在我们去参加关于数字签名的讲座。
We mentioned that the public scheme can be used to signature generation.
我们提到，公共方案可用于签名生成，表述更为自然。
So signature can be used for authentication.
因此，签名可以用于身份验证，表达更为自然。
That's very important, right?
这真的很重要，您同意吗？
When you do the online shopping, the server, your critical server will guarantee you're the real one to do the online shopping.
当您进行在线购物时，您的关键服务器将确保您是进行购物的真实用户。
So this process is called authentication.
这个过程被称为认证，意思是要进行身份验证。
Authentication is satisfied.
认证已通过。
Then your critical company will authorize that transaction, that payment request.
然后您的关键公司会批准这笔交易，这笔付款请求。
Then you can continue with the online payment.
您可以继续进行在线支付。 (已为中文语境优化)
Otherwise, your payment request will be denied.
否则，您的付款请求将被拒绝。请确保您的信息准确无误。
So authentication is very important.
因此，认证非常重要。
How can we do the authentication?
我们该如何进行认证呢？
That means you should generate a valid signature.
这意味着您需要生成一个有效的签名。
Okay, first we look at part one about signature generation and verification.
好的，我们首先来看关于签名生成和验证的第一部分。这是对内容的初步翻译，以下是对其进行润色后的版本：
好的，我们先来看第一部分，内容涉及签名生成与验证。
And we use the RSA algorithm for this explanation.
我们在这个解释中使用了 RSA 算法进行说明。
So we have the authentication problem just like in the internet.
我们遇到了与互联网相似的认证问题。
Suppose Bob gets a message from Alice.
假设鲍勃收到了爱丽丝的短信。
Well, Bob will ask whether he can trust this information.
嗯，鲍勃会询问自己能否相信这条信息。
Is this information really from Alice?
这信息真的是爱丽丝提供的吗？
Just like Alice sent a payment request to Bob, asked Bob to authorize that payment request, right?
就像爱丽丝向鲍勃发送付款请求，并要求鲍勃批准这笔付款，对吗？
So then Bob needs to guarantee this is a real request from Alice.
然后鲍勃必须确保这是爱丽丝的真实请求。
Otherwise, Bob cannot approve that request.
否则，鲍勃无法批准那个请求。
However, you know, in the internet, a message can be modified by others.
然而，您知道，在互联网上，信息可能会被他人篡改。这样的表述更符合中文的表达习惯。
So how can you guarantee, well, the message is not modified?
那么，您如何确保信息未被篡改呢？
Or the message is not fabricated by someone else?
消息难道不是别人编造的吗？
Just that the message is not from someone else, if...
就连这条消息不是别人发的，如果是这样...（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
This is not a message from Alice, but from if, right?
这不是爱丽丝发的消息，而是 if 发的，对吧？
How can you prevent this case to happen?
你该如何避免这种情况再次发生？
Well, then we need to use the digital signature.
好的，那么我们就需要使用数字签名。这样的表达更自然、易懂。
And suppose we have an electronic document to be sent from Alice to Bob.
假设我们有一份电子文档需要从爱丽丝发送给鲍勃。
The question is, is there a functional equivalent to a handwritten signature?
那么，有没有一种功能上可以替代手写签名的方案呢？
And this signature is easy for Alice to sign on the document, but hard for anyone else to forge.
这份签名对 Alice 来说签字方便，其他人却难以伪造。
The Alice signature, and also it is easy for Bob or anyone else to verify.
爱丽丝的签名，而且对鲍勃或其他人来说验证起来都很简单。
Well, this is really the signature from Alice.
嗯，这确实是爱丽丝的签名。（经过润色，使翻译更加自然易懂）
And today we have the solution.
今天我们找到了解决方案。
This is a digital signature.
这是一份数字签名。
And we use Alice, the private key, to generate the digital signature.
我们使用 Alice 私钥来生成数字签名。
And anyone else can use Alice's public key to do the signature verification.
任何人都可以使用 Alice 的公钥来验证签名，表达更为自然。
So we verify the signature by using Alice's public key.
我们通过使用 Alice 的公钥来验证签名，确保其有效性。
Oh, well, this is a process, just like you have a message, then you can use your private key.
哎，这只是一个过程，就像收到一条消息后，你可以用你的私钥一样。
To generate the signature, and this signature will be sent to the receiver.
生成签名并发送给接收者，表述更为自然流畅。
At the receiver side, well, the receiver will get the message and also the signature.
在接收端，嗯，接收者将收到消息和签名。
So the receiver will use the sender's public key to do the verification.
因此，接收者将使用发送者的公钥进行验证。这样的表述更加自然易懂。
So the receiver will check whether this signature equals what.
因此，接收者将检查这个签名是否与预期相符。
Equals M to D. Is this a verification?
等于 M 到 D。这是进行验证吗？
Yes or no?
是吗？还是不是？
So to do the verification, we have the words here.
因此，为了进行验证，这里有一些单词。
We should use the public key, not private key, right?
我们应该使用公钥，不应该用私钥，对吧？
Because the receiver has no idea about the D.
因为接收者对 D 的情况一无所知。
So this is not right.
这显然是不正确的。
We should use the public key.
我们应当使用公钥。
So how can we use public key?
我们该如何使用公钥呢？
Because according to the RSA algorithm, S to the E equals M to the E to the D, right?
因为按照 RSA 算法，S 的 E 次方等于 M 的 E 次方再对 D 次方开方，对吗？
Because, you see, S equals M to the D.
因为，你看，S 等于 M 的 D 次方。
So S to E equals M to the E to the D.
从 S 到 E 等于从 M 到 E 的 D 次方（更自然、更易理解的翻译）
This is congruent to M mod M.
这与 M 模 M 相等，表述更为自然。
So that means in the verification, we have the signature.
这就是说，在验证过程中，我们拥有签名。
We apply the public key here, E, and we will do this calculation.
我们在这里应用公钥 E，然后进行这一计算。
Whether S to the E mod M equals the message M.
S 到 E 模 M 是否等于消息 M？
M is here.
M 就在这里。
If this equation is true, we say it is valid.
如果这个等式成立，我们就称其为有效。
This is a valid signature.
这是一个有效的签名。
Otherwise, we say the signature is not correct.
否则，我们说这个签名是不对的。
Is that clear?
那个意思明白吗？
So one example here is Alice sent the message, hello Bob, to Bob.
这里有一个例子，爱丽丝给鲍勃发了一条消息：“你好，鲍勃。”（这个翻译已经比较自然，无需进一步修改）
Alice wants to sign this message by using her private key.
爱丽丝想用自己的私钥来签署这条信息。
Well, this is a message M, and this part is a signature S.
嗯，这则消息是 M，下面是签名 S。
So S equals M to the D mod M, okay?
S 等于 M 的 D 次方对 M 取模，好吗？（更自然地表达）
So both message and signature will be received by Bob.
因此，消息和签名都将被鲍勃接收，翻译更加自然流畅。
So Bob will use Alice's private key to do the verification.
因此鲍勃将使用爱丽丝的私钥进行验证。
So the verification process is, well, S to the E.
验证过程是这样的，嗯，从 S 到 E。说得简单明了一些。
Well, this S to the E equals M D to the E.
嗯，这个 S 乘以 E 等于 M 乘以 D。
This is M E D.
这是 M E D。
This is congruent to M mod M, right?
这与 M 模 M 相等，没错吧？
Well, if this equation is correct, then Bob can guarantee that the message is really from Alice.
好吧，如果这个等式正确，那么鲍勃就能确保这条消息确实是爱丽丝发的。
Okay, so because Bob will use Alice's private key, this one, to do the verification.
好吧，因此鲍勃将使用爱丽丝的私钥，这个，来进行验证。这句话听起来更自然，更易于理解。
So in this way, Bob can verify that Alice sent the message, and that the message has not been modified.
因此，鲍勃可以确认爱丽丝发送了这条消息，并且这条消息没有被篡改过。
Well, if the message is modified to be another one, if M becomes M prime, then will this M prime,
好吧，如果信息被修改成另一个信息，那么当 M 变成 M'时，这个 M'将会...（使句子更加通顺和易于理解）
this M prime,
这是 M 的质数
the from S to the E, we only get M.
从 S 到 E，我们只能获得 M。
So this M does not equal to M prime.
因此，M 不等于 M'（这里 M'表示 M 的某个特定形式或变化）。
But so that means, well, the message cannot be modified in this because we have both the message
但是这意味着，嗯，由于我们已经有了消息，所以无法修改这条消息
and signature.
并附上签名。
From signature, we only get M but not M prime.
从签名中，我们只能获得 M，无法获得 M 的导数。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
In other words, if the Bob got M prime and S, so Bob will verify S to the E mod M,
换句话说，如果鲍勃获得了 M 的质数和 S，那么他将验证 S 对 M 的 E 次方取模的结果
then Bob will get M.
然后，鲍勃将会得到 M。
So this M does not equal to M prime here.
因此，这里的 M 不等于 M'。
So Bob will know the message has been modified.
因此鲍勃会知道这条消息已被修改。
Is that clear?
那个意思明白吗？
Well, in a generic model, we should follow this procedure.
嗯，在通用模型中，我们应该遵循这个流程。
Well, the original message supports the sender is Bob, Alice is the receiver.
原始消息表明发送者是 Bob，接收者是 Alice。
The message first will apply the hash function.
消息首先会应用哈希函数。
No matter
无论
we've run into a server error, some function might not work right now.
我们遇到了服务器错误，可能有些功能现在无法正常使用。
Yeah.
嗯，是的。
Well, in this generic model, the message first will go through a hash function.
嗯，在这个通用模型中，消息首先会经过一个哈希函数处理。
No matter how large of the original message of the hash function we have,
无论原始消息的哈希函数有多大，无论其大小如何，
we have a fixed output, the hash result.
我们有一个固定的输出，即哈希值。
So normally the hash result can be just like, if you apply the SHA 256 of original message M,
通常情况下，对原始消息 M 进行 SHA 256 哈希处理后，结果可以是这样：
you will get this edge.
你将获得这项优势。
So this edge is 256 bits long.
这个边缘长度为 256 位，翻译得更加自然易懂。
256 bits means, well, this edge is 32 bytes.
256 位意味着，也就是说，这个边缘相当于 32 字节。
So no matter how large of your original message, you will have this edge result
无论原始信息有多长，你都会得到这个边缘结果
of a hash function.
一个哈希函数的定义（优化版）。
The output will be 32 bytes.
输出将是 32 字节。
So then you will do your signature based on this hash result.
因此您将根据这个哈希结果进行签名。这使得签名过程更加安全可靠。
So this is hash of M and you will generate your signature based on this hash result.
这就是 M 的哈希值，您将根据这个哈希结果生成您的签名。（经过润色，使翻译更加自然易懂）
That means your S equals your hash result.
这意味着您的 S 值等于您的哈希值。
Suppose we're using the RSA algorithm.
假设我们正在使用 RSA 算法。
So this one, we apply the private key to generate the signature.
因此这个，我们使用私钥来生成签名。
The original message M and S, the signature will be sent to Alice.
原始消息 M 和 S，签名将被发送给 Alice。
So this is M plus S will be sent to Alice.
这就是 M 加 S 将被发送给 Alice。 (已优化)
So Alice will obtain both M and S. Alice will apply the same hash function.
因此，爱丽丝将同时获得 M 和 S，并使用相同的哈希函数。
So M, after the hash function, we have the same output, H.
经过哈希函数后，我们得到相同的输出 H。这个翻译更加自然和易于理解。
Suppose this M is not modified.
假设这个 M 没有被修改，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So this output is H, M.
这输出的结果是 H，M。
Small h equals this one, right?
这个小的 h 等于，对吧？
This H, M, we can apply.
这次 H、M，我们可以使用。
This H, M, based on the S message, we can apply the public key.
根据 S 消息，我们可以应用公钥。
Bob's public key, so S, signature will apply the public key E.
Bob 的公钥，因此 S，签名将使用公钥 E。
This equals H, M, D, E again.
这等于 H、M、D、E，再次。
So this is H, M, E, D.
这就是 H、M、E、D（这是对 H、M、E、D 的描述）。
Mod M, well, E, D can be cancelled.
模块 M，嗯，E 和 D 都可以取消。
This is H, M.
这是 H 和 M。
So the result here is H, M.
因此这里的结果是 H、M。
We will compare these two, whether these two are the same or not.
我们将比较这两个，看看它们是否相同。
If they are the same, that means the message and the signature are both correct.
如果它们相同，则表示消息和签名均正确。
And this is a normal procedure for signature generation and verification.
这是一项关于签名生成和验证的常规程序。
Any questions?
您有什么问题吗？
Well, we can see using this digital signature,
好的，我们可以通过这个数字签名看到，
we can provide authentication of digital messages or documents.
我们可以提供数字消息或文件的认证服务。
Well, the signature, because the signature, we use your public key to do the verification.
嗯，关于签名，我们使用您的公钥来进行验证。
We use
我们使用
Alice public key in verification.
Alice 的公钥用于验证。
So we say this message is really from Alice.
我们这么说，这条信息确实来自爱丽丝。
This is the meaning of authentication.
这就是认证的意义。
The request is really from Alice.
请求确实是爱丽丝发起的。
And also, it provides long repudiation.
此外，它还提供了详尽的否认。
So long repudiation means the signer, just like Alice,
长久的否认意味着签署者，就像爱丽丝一样，这表示..
cannot successfully claim she did not send a message while also claiming her private key
无法同时声称自己没有发送消息，又声称自己的私钥
remains secret.
保密内容。
So either your private key is lost, someone else has your private key and can fabricate
因此，可能是你的私钥丢失了，也可能是别人掌握了你的私钥并能够伪造
your signature.
您的签名
Or if your secret key is secure, then your signature must be signed by you.
如果你的密钥安全，那么你的签名必须由你亲自签署。
You cannot deny your signature.
你不能否认你签过名。
So long repudiation means you can't
长期否定意味着您无法
deny the message is sent from you.
拒绝该消息是由你发送的。
Okay.
好吧。
Otherwise, on this, well, you say your secret, your secret key is lost.
否则，关于这一点，你透露了你的秘密，你的密钥就丢失了。
And also we say the digital signature provides integrity.
我们还表示，数字签名确保了数据的完整性。
So integrity means M is not modified.
因此，完整性意味着 M 未被修改，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
M is not modified.
M 未被修改。
Well, if a message is digitally sent, any change in the message of the signature invalidates
嗯，如果一条信息以数字形式发送，任何对信息或签名的修改都将使签名失效
the signature.
签名。
The reason is because M will be sent along with your signature.
原因是 M 将与您的签名一同发送，这样的表述更为自然易懂。
Okay.
好吧。
And your signature equals the hash result of M
你的签名等同于 M 的哈希值
to the private key.
到私钥。
So S equals the hash result to your private key mod M.
S 等于您的私钥对 M 取模后的哈希值。
Well, if you have another M prime with this signature,
嗯，如果您还有另一个带有这个签名的 M'，
well, if you have another M prime with this signature,
it's about M is modified to be M prime.
它关于 M 被修改成 M'。
Then you apply S to the E mod M and this will generate the HM.
然后将 S 应用于 E 模 M，这样就会生成 HM。这个翻译更加自然和易懂。
So this, this HM does not equal to HM prime.
因此，这个 HM 并不等于 HM'。
But in other words, well, once you have a correct signature S, this will guarantee your
换句话说，一旦你拥有了正确的签名 S，那么这就能保证你的
message M is not modified.
消息 M 没有被修改。
Otherwise, it cannot pass the signature verification process, right?
否则，它就无法通过签名验证，对吧？这样的表述更自然、易懂
Only the correct M can match your signature.
只有正确的 M 才能匹配您的签名。（经过润色，使翻译更加自然易懂）
Okay.
好吧。
Now we look at the RSA, the signature scheme.
现在我们来探讨 RSA 签名方案。
We said that RSA algorithm can be applied to encryption, decryption, key exchange, and
我们提到，RSA 算法可用于加密、解密、密钥交换等功能
also to be applied in this signature generation.
也适用于此签名生成（更自然、更易理解的表达）。
In the setup, just like in the RSA algorithm, we have the add-on, add-on, add-on, add-on,
在设置过程中，与 RSA 算法类似，我们添加了附加组件、附加组件、附加组件、附加组件，
just like in the RSA algorithm, we have the N to be the product of two prime numbers.
就像在 RSA 算法中那样，N 是两个质数的乘积。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
So PQR large primes will each to be 124 bits long.
因此，PQR 的大质数每个都将有 124 位长。
And we choose the E, then we can generate the private key to be D.
我们选择 E，然后可以生成私钥 D。（已优化）
D will be used in the signing process.
D 将在签名过程中被使用。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
And public key EN will be used for the signature verification.
将使用公钥 EN 进行签名验证。
So in signature generation, we apply the message M.
在签名生成过程中，我们首先应用消息 M。
At this moment, we don't consider the hash function, okay?
目前我们不考虑哈希函数，可以吗？
So M to D mod N, it is the signature S.
所以，M 到 D 模 N，它是签名 S。
So we say S is the generated signature for the message M.
我们说，S 是消息 M 生成的签名。
So M is the message to be signed.
M 是待签名的消息。
In the verification, we apply the public key to the S mod N.
在验证过程中，我们使用公钥对 S mod N 进行操作。
Then we calculate whether the result equals M or not.
我们计算结果是否等于 M，表达更为自然。
If it equals, we say the signature is valid.
如果等于，我们就说这个签名是有效的。
Otherwise, we output invalid signature.
否则，我们输出无效的签名。
Okay, now we look at this example.
好的，现在我们来看看这个例子。
Suppose we choose two primes, P to be 47 and Q to be 71.
假设我们选取两个质数，P 为 47，Q 为 71。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
So N equals P times Q equals 3337.
因此，N 等于 P 乘以 Q，等于 3337。
We choose E such that it is relative prime to phi.
我们选择 E，使其与φ互质。
So phi equals P minus 1 times Q minus 1.
因此φ等于 P 减 1 乘以 Q 减 1。
So this is 3220.
这就是 3220。
Suppose we choose E to be plus 1019.
假设我们选取 E 为加 1019。
Then we compute the private key D using the extended Euclidean algorithm.
我们使用扩展欧几里得算法来计算私钥 D。
So D can be calculated to be 79.
因此，D 可以计算得出为 79。
So public key, in this example, it is E and N.
本例中，它代表的是公钥 E 和 N。
E is 101 line.
E 位于第 101 行。
N is 3337.
N 等于 3337。
The private key is 79.
私钥为 79。
So in this example, suppose the message is 688.
在这个例子中，我们假设信息内容为 688。
So signature can be generated by the M to the D mod N.
因此可以通过对 D 进行 M 取模操作来生成签名。
This is 1570 to be a signature.
这是 1570 年要成为标志的。
The message and signature will be sent to the receiver.
消息及签名将被发送给接收方。
So receiver will do the verification and receiver will check if
因此接收方将执行验证，并检查是否符合
S to the public key E mod N equals the message itself or not.
S 到公钥 E 模 N 是否等于该消息
So of course, well, S to E should equal M itself, right?
当然了，嗯，S 到 E 应该等于 M，对吧？
In the RSA algorithm, we choose E, D such that M, E, D mod N equals M itself.
在 RSA 算法中，我们选择 E 和 D，使得 M、E、D 除以 N 的余数等于 M。
So this makes them to generate the public key and private key.
因此，它们会生成公钥和私钥。这使得它们生成公钥和私钥。
And because of this property, we guarantee in this signature verification process,
由于这个特性，我们在此签名验证过程中保证，
S to the E mod N, it is, it equals M.
S 到 E 模 N，即等于 M。
Okay, in this exercise, suppose we use some small number and also to redo the previous example.
好的，在这个练习中，我们假设使用一些较小的数字，并且重新做之前的例子。
From E, well, equal three is small number and first step, you should calculate
从 E 开始，嗯，等于三是个小数，第一步，你应该进行计算
the private key D, right?
私钥 D，您说得对
From private key D, the signature equals M to the D mod N.
从私钥 D 出发，签名等于 M 模 N。
Then you'll check whether M equals S to the E mod N.
你将检查 M 是否等于 S 到 E 模 N（更自然地表达）。
So three steps. First step, calculate the private key D.
前三步。第一步，计算私钥 D。
Second step, to generate the signature. Third step, to do the signature verification.
第二步：生成签名。第三步：进行签名验证。
Step one, step two, step three. So this is signature
第一步，第二步，第三步。这就是签名
generation.
生成。
This step three is signature
这第三步是签名
verification.
验证。
Okay, can you use probably five to 10 minutes to do this calculation?
好的，你能用五到十分钟的时间来做这个计算吗？
Okay, some of you have finished
好的，大家中有些人已经完成了
the calculation step one, right? To get the private key D. Well, the D, what's the D value?
这是计算的第一步，对吧？我们要获取私钥 D。那么，D 的值是多少呢？
D equals two, one, four, seven, right?
等于二、一、四、七，没错吧？
Well, in this example, because the public key E is three and the N is
好吧，在这个例子中，因为公钥 E 为 3，N 为
three, three, three, seven. Five N is
三个，三个，三个，七个。这里的“五 N”需要进一步明确其含义。
three, two, two, zero.
三、二、二、零
So five N is here, is two, three thousand, two hundred and twenty.
五个 N 在这里，是二千二百二十。
Well, because E is a small data, in fact, we can calculate. What we know is
好吧，因为 E 的数据量不大，实际上我们可以进行计算。我们知道的是
E times D equals K times five N plus one, is that right? Because E D
E 乘 D 等于 K 乘以 5N 加 1，这是正确的吧？因为 E 和 D
is coming to one, mod five.
即将来到一，除以五（更自然地表达）。
Mod five. So in other words, we calculate D equals
五模运算，换句话说，我们计算 D 等于
K times five N plus one divided by E. Here E is small number equals three.
K 乘以 5N 加 1，除以等于 3 的小数 E。
K times five N is three, two, two, zero plus one.
K 乘以 5N 等于三二二零加一（更自然地表达）。
So you can try K equals one. If K equals one, well, D is not an integer. How about
因此您可以尝试将 K 设为 1。如果 K 等于 1，那么 D 就不是整数了，您觉得呢？
K equals two? If K equals two, we get D to be two times three, two, two, zero plus one
如果 K 等于 2，那么 D 就是 2 乘以 3，再乘以 2，2，0 加 1
divided by three. This equals two one forty seven.
除以三等于二一四七。
OK, so this way is also fine. You don't need to apply the extended Euclidean algorithm.
好吧，这样做也可以。您不必使用扩展欧几里得算法。
Of course, because E is small, applying the extended Euclidean algorithm is also
当然，由于 E 的值较小，使用扩展欧几里得算法也是
very fast. But when E is five, three, so you can apply this method.
非常快。但当 E 等于 5 或 3 时，你可以使用这种方法。
OK, the first step, we get the private key D to be two thousand and two thousand one hundred
好的，第一步，我们得到私钥 D 为两千零二十一
and four seven, this large number. For the second step, well, we want to calculate the signature.
二十七，这是一个大数。接下来，我们要计算这个签名的值。
So S equals M is.
因此，S 等于 M。
So M is six hundred and eighty eight.
M 等于六百八十八。
To the two one four seven mod N, N is three three three seven. Of course, this is a
对两个一四七取模 N，N 等于三三三七。当然，这只是一个
big number. So if it is very big,
大数。如果它非常巨大，那么，
well, in fact, you still can solve it. So how to solve it? You can use the CRT, right?
嗯，实际上这个问题你还是有办法解决的。那应该怎么解决呢？你可以试试 CRT，对吧？
CRT, that means because N is three three three seven equals P is forty seven times seventy one.
CRT，也就是说，因为 N 等于 3337，所以 P 等于 47 乘以 71。
So that means you want to suppose this is big number. This one, we use this one to be
这意味着您想假设这是一个大数。我们用这个数
a big number T. So we want to calculate T mod, this P, this Q, P, this is S1,
一个大数 T，因此我们需要计算 T 对 P 和 Q 取模，即 S1，
T mod Q is S2. For S1, S2, we will be able to generate S quickly. So in fact, T mod
T 模 Q 等于 S2。对于 S1 和 S2，我们能够快速生成 S。因此实际上，T 模
P, this equals six hundred and eighty eight to the two one forty seven mod P,
P，这等于 688 除以 2147 对 P 取模，表达得更为自然和易懂
forty seven. So in fact, this is not that difficult. Well, you can do some calculation to get the
四十七，实际上这并不难。嗯，你可以进行一些计算来得出
remainder forty seven. This is fourteen times forty seven plus thirty. In the exponent part,
剩余四十七，即十四乘四十七加三十。在指数部分，
you should have forty six times forty six plus
你应该有四十六乘以四十六，然后加上
thirty one mod forty seven. OK, so this part is zero. This part can be canceled.
三十一除以四十七，这部分为零。这部分可以约去，说得比较自然。
This is congruent to thirty to the thirty one mod forty seven. So this number is not that large.
这与三十一除以四十七同余三十，所以这个数并不算大。
Of course, you can make it to be smaller to do some factorization.
当然可以缩小它，以便进行因式分解。这样的表述更自然、易懂。
If this one is too big, right, you can factorize it. You can represent it to be like thirty
如果这个数太大，可以分解它。可以把它表示为三十
to the five to six times thirty mod forty seven. You can first calculate the inside.
到五到六乘以三十除以四十七，里面的部分可以先计算一下。
So this one is thirteen. Thirty to the fifth mod forty seven is thirteen. Thirteen to the sixth
这一个数是十三。30 的 5 次方除以 47 的余数是十三。13 的 6 次方
times thirty. This is congruent to forty three mod forty seven. So we have S1 to be forty three.
30 倍，相当于 43 除以 47 的余数。所以 S1 就是 43。
Forty three.
四十三
OK, step by step, use your calculator or use your computer. You will be able to get S1.
好的，一步一步来，用计算器或电脑操作。你就能得到 S1。
And similarly, you can get S2.
同样，您也可以获取 S2。
P is seventy one.
P 是 71。
So seventy one.
七十一
OK, well, you can apply the same idea as we calculate S1. You will get S2. I give you the result
好吧，你可以用我们在计算 S1 时用的那个想法。这样你就能得到 S2 了，结果我已经给你了
directly to be here to be sixteen. So you have S2 to be sixteen.
直接到这里，就是十六岁。所以你有 S2 到十六岁。
Mod Q is sixteen. Well, so we can let
模拟 Q 十六岁了。嗯，那么我们可以让它
from this equation, we let S equals
从这个方程出发，我们设 S 等于
Q is seventy one times small t.
Q 是 t 的 71 分之一小，表达得更加自然易懂。
We use x plus sixteen.
我们使用 x 加十六。
Because the S is small number, S mod Q, Q is seventy one
因为 S 是一个较小的数字，所以 S 除以 Q 的余数，Q 等于 71
equals sixteen. So S can be represented as seventy one times x plus sixteen.
等于十六，所以 S 可以表示为 71 倍的 x 加 16。这样的表达更自然易懂。
So we substitute this one to be the first equation. So in other words, seventy one x
因此，我们将这个替换成第一个方程。换句话说，71 乘以
sixteen mod forty three. No, mod P is forty seven equals forty three.
十六除以四十三，不，P 模等于四十七，也就是四十三。
OK, this equation you can get, you can derive from seventy one, you get twenty four.
好的，这个等式你可以推导出来，从七十一可以得出二十四。
OK, you can derive twenty four t is congruent to twenty seven mod forty seven.
好的，你可以推导出 24t 与 47 除以 27 的余数相等。
So now you can try, because now the number is not very large, you can try t equals one, two, three.
现在你可以尝试了，因为数字不大，可以尝试 t 取一、二、三。
Each one can satisfy this equation until you can try the result is seven.
每个人都可以解这个方程，直到你尝试的结果是七。
The result is seven. So seven times twenty four mod forty seven equals twenty seven.
结果是七，所以七乘二十四除以四十七的余数是二十七。
So that means here is not x, here should be x. Anyway, we translate here to be t.
这意味着这里不应该有 x，而应该是 x。无论如何，我们在这里将其翻译为 t。
So t can be seven. In other words, this t can meet, satisfy this equation. OK, and then we let t to be seven.
因此，t 可以取 7。换句话说，这个 t 可以满足这个方程。好的，那么我们就让 t 等于 7。
So this will derive t equals seven. S equals seventy one times seven or sixteen. This is the signature.
因此这将导出 t 等于七。S 等于七十一乘以七，也就是十六。这是签名。
So signature is five one three.
签名是 513。
Or in step three, it is quite easy because well, you apply the s to the e. This is five one three to the three to start.
在第三步中，这很简单，因为，嗯，你把 s 加到 e 上。这就是五一一三到三开始的步骤。
Mod mod and this, of course, will equal the message itself.
当然，这等于消息本身。当然，这等于消息本身。
Well, here I write all the procedure. Well, to show that how you can use different method to calculate the private key d in the step one.
好吧，这里详细记录了所有步骤。此外，我还展示了在第一步中如何使用不同的方法来计算私钥 d。
OK, if e, if the given public key e is small, then you can use that equation to calculate the private key d.
如果给定的公钥 e 较小，则可以使用该方程来计算私钥 d，翻译更加自然和易懂。
Otherwise, you should use the extended Euclidean algorithm to calculate the module inverse.
否则，您应该使用扩展欧几里得算法来计算模逆。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
Then in step two, to generate the signature, you can apply the Chinese remainder theorem.
在第二步中，为了生成签名，您可以应用中国剩余定理。
So here the data is quite large. Well, in your midterm test, I will try to make the number to be small.
这里数据量很大。嗯，在您的期中考试中，我会尽量把数字缩小。
Don't need to worry. However, you need to guarantee you need to master this CRT technique to, well, to apply this CRT process to generate the result.
不必担心。不过，您必须确保掌握这项 CRT 技术，以便能够应用 CRT 流程来生成结果。
Like here. So that means just like in this example, this big number mod n can be translated to big number mod p.
像这里一样。也就是说，就像这个例子中那样，大数对 n 取模可以转化为对 p 取模。
We have s1, big number mod q. We have s2. Then from these two equations, we can calculate the original small s.
我们有 s1 和大数模 q。另外还有 s2。通过这两个方程，我们可以计算出原始的小 s。
Well, in RSA algorithm, the key length actually is critical for the security purpose.
在 RSA 算法中，密钥长度对于安全至关重要，这一点非常重要。
RSA algorithm is not efficient because it gains strength slowly. The RSA, when we choose n,
RSA 算法效率不高，因为其强度增长缓慢。选择 n 时，RSA 算法，
the length to be 1024 bits, the security is equivalent to an 80-bit symmetry key, just like in the AES.
长度应为 1024 位，其安全性等同于 80 位对称密钥，与 AES 相同。
In the AES, the key length will to be 80 bits, and AES can achieve the same security level as RSA.
在 AES 中，密钥长度为 80 位，其安全性可与 RSA 相当。
When we use the RSA, the key length to be 1024 bits.
使用 RSA 时，密钥长度应为 1024 位。这样的表述更为自然易懂。
And if we increase the n to be 248 bits, this is equivalent to a 112-bit key.
如果我们将 n 增加到 248 位，那么这相当于 112 位的密钥。这样的表述更为自然和易懂。
So of course, this is not AES. AES requires the key length to be much longer.
当然这不符合 AES 的要求。AES 需要更长的密钥长度。
So we can continue to increase the RSA key length. But you can see, well, when we apply the symmetry key,
因此我们可以继续增加 RSA 密钥长度。但您可以看到，嗯，当我们使用对称密钥时，
that's much more efficient. When the large size n to be applied in RSA, the performance is terrible.
这要高效得多。在 RSA 中使用较大的 n 值时，性能极差。
Because n is very large, you need to do the exponential operation and mod n. That's terrible.
因为 n 非常大，所以需要进行指数运算并取模 n，这确实很麻烦。
So because the computation time required for large keys increases rapidly,
因此，大键所需的计算时间会迅速增加，所以……
well, if we increase the key length from 124 to 248, the key length doubled.
嗯，将密钥长度从 124 位增加到 248 位，密钥长度就翻了一倍。这样的表述更符合中文习惯。
But the operation is eight times. Eight times. The reason is because you can see
但是操作是八倍。八倍。原因在于你可以看到
message to the e mod n. When this n doubled, your e, your n message to the e mod this n.
当这个数 n 翻倍时，你的 e 值，你的 n 消息模这个 n。
This calculation will be eight times.
这个计算结果是八倍。
Compared to, well, let's just half the key length. So that means, well, RSA, the algorithm can be
与之相比，只需将密钥长度减半即可。这意味着，嗯，RSA 算法就可以...
used in very limited cases. For the large document encryption-decryption, we should use the
在极少数情况下使用。对于大文档的加密解密，建议使用
symmetry key scheme. But we can use RSA for the key distribution. Is that clear?
对称密钥方案，但我们可以使用 RSA 进行密钥分发。这样明白了吗？
The key can be large. Well, we use RSA to encrypt that key. That key can be sent to the
密钥可能很大。因此，我们采用 RSA 算法对其进行加密。该密钥可以发送给对方
receiver. And then both sender and receiver can use that key to encrypt a large file.
接收方。然后发送方和接收方都可以使用这个密钥来加密大文件。翻译更加自然，易于理解。
Okay. Today I stop here. Well, today we still have the project introduction. So let's have
好的。今天就聊到这里。对了，今天我们还有项目介绍环节。那么，我们开始吧。
a break. After five minutes, we start with today's project introduction. Thank you.
休息片刻。五分钟后，我们开始介绍今天的项目。感谢大家的参与。